Guide to the Union Printing Company records 1909-1966
Western Washington University, Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
Union Printing Company records
1909-1966
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies Goltz-Murray Building 808 25th St Bellingham, WA 98225-9123 Phone: 360 650 7534 Email: cpnws@wwu.edu
XOE_CPNWS0072unionprintingco
Union Printing Company
15 linear feet
The collection includes the business records of the Union Printing Company.
The Union Printing Company was established in 1898, incorporated in 1902, and operated until 1996 as a printing, binding and stationary business in present-day Bellingham, Washington. In 1910 the company merged with three other local printers and expanded its operations considerably. Most of its clients were local businesses and individuals, although some business was generated from Seattle, Spokane, and San Francisco. Throughout its history the Union Printing Company acquired land and assets from its clients to pay debts they owed, including those of the La Conner Mail newspaper. The Union Printing Company closed in 1996.
The Union Printing Company records document the establishment and growth of this printing and binding operation based in present-day Bellingham, Washington. Company records span the period 1871 to 1971, with the bulk dated from 1924 to 1954. The collection comprises administrative, financial, personnel and property records. Administrative records include articles of incorporation, while financial records document the company's business interactions with local individuals and companies. Personnel records include names of the individuals employed by the Union Printing Company. Property records reflect the company's acquisition of land and assets in Whatcom and Skagit Counties, including those of the La Conner Mail newspaper.
The Union Printing Company records are organized in accordance with the following series and subseries arrangement:
Series I: Administrative Records, 1910-1971
Incorporation Records, 1910-1929
Correspondence, 1926, 1960
Series II: Financial Records, 1923-1954
Series III: Personnel, 1924-1953
Series IV: Property Records, 1871-1940
Series V: Publications, 1939-1948, undated
The collection is open to the public.
Donated by Kenneth R. Nuckolls of the Union Printing Company.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Union Printing Company
Whatcom County (Wash.) -- History -- Sources -- Maps.; Whatcom County (Wash.) -- Economic conditions -- History -- Sources.
Printing -- Bellingham (Wash.) -- History -- Sources.; Printing machinery and supplies -- Bellingham (Wash.) -- History -- Sources.; Bookbinding -- Bellingham (Wash.) -- History -- Sources.; Business enterprises -- Washington (State) -- Bellingham -- History -- Sources.; Retail trade -- Washington (State) -- Bellingham -- History -- Sources.; Depressions -- 1929 -- Washington (State) -- Whatcom County -- History -- Sources.
Publishers and Publishing; Bellingham
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Administrative Records, 1910-1971; Series I
  - Incorporation Records, 1910-1929; Subseries 1
    - Articles of Incorporation and Amendments, 1910, 1917, 1926, 1929 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Trademark Application, 1924 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Correspondence, 1926, 1960; Subseries 2
    - Standard Oil, 1926, 1960 (Box-folder 1/3)
- Financial Records, 1923-1954; Series 2
  - Balance Sheets (annual summary), 1925-1931 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Balance Sheets (annual summary), 1932-1938 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Bank Books, 1926-1950 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Cash Book, 1925 February 2 - 1927 March 16 (Volume Volume 1)
  - Cash Book, 1927 March 1 - 1929 January 31 (Volume Volume 2)
  - Cash Book, 1929 February 1 - 1930 September 30 (Volume Volume 3)
  - Cash Book, 1930 Octobter 1 - 1932 April 30 (Volume Volume 4)
  - Cash Book, 1932 May 2 - 1934 March 31 (Volume Volume 5)
  - Cash Book, 1934 April 2 - 1935 April 30 (Volume Volume 6)
  - Cash Book, 1935 May 1 - 1936 September 8 (Volume Volume 7)
  - Cash Book, 1936 September 18 - 1937 December 24 (Volume Volume 8)
  - Cash Book, 1937 Dec. 24 - 1939 April 28 (Volume Volume 9)
  - Cash Book, 1939 April 28 - 1940 September 12 (Volume Volume 10)
  - Cash Book, 1940 Sept 12 - 1942 January 31 (Volume Volume 11)
  - Cash Book, 1942 February 3 - 1943 August 10 (Volume Volume 12)
  - Cash Book, 1943 August 11- 1944 December 29 (Volume Volume 13)
  - Cash Book, 1944 December 29 - 1946 April 5 (Volume Volume 14)
  - Cash Book, 1946 April 5 - 1947 July 31 (Volume Volume 15)
  - Cash Book, 1947 August 7 - 1949 December 30 (Volume Volume 16)
  - Cash Book, 1950 January 6 - 1952 June 25 (Volume Volume 17)
  - Cash Book, 1952 July 3 - 1954 January 29 (Volume Volume 18)
  - Closing Papers, 1924-1925 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Closing Papers, 1925-1926 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Closing Papers, 1926-1927 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Contract & Bill of Sale of Printing Equipment, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Income Tax Returns, 1923-1926, 1931 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Inventory of Materials, 1925 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Ledger Book(including Cash Printing Jobs), 1924 September 2 - 1925 January 31 (Volume Volume 19)
  - Ledger Book, 1925 February 9 - 1930 November 18 (Volume Volume 20)
  - Ledger Book, 1930 November 12 - 1939 January 31 (Volume Volume 21)
  - Ledger Book, 1939 February 28 - 1947 April 15 (Volume Volume 22)
  - Mortgage of Equipment, 1967 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Notice of Attachment of Stock, 1934 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Purchase Record, 1925 January 31 - 1930 September 30 (Volume Volume 22)
- Personnel, 1924-1953; Series II
  - Time Book, 1924 July 26 - 1927 June 18 (Volume Volume 24)
  - Time Book, 1927 June 25 - 1930 April 12 (Volume Volume 25)
  - Time Book, 1930 April 19 - 1933 March 10 (Volume Volume 26)
  - Time Book, 1933 March 16 - 1935 December 26 (Volume Volume 27)
  - Time Book, 1936 January 2 - 1941August 21 (Volume Volume 28)
  - Pay Roll/Expense notes, 1938 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Time Book, 1941 August 28 - 1943 August 26 (Volume Volume 29)
  - Time Book, 1943 September 2 - 1945 November 29 (Volume Volume 30)
  - Pay Roll purchase of War Bonds, Withholding Tables, 1945 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Time Book, 1945 December 6 - 1946 June 13 (Volume Volume 31)
  - Time Book, 1946 June 13 - 1947 August 7 (Volume Volume 32)
  - Time Book, 1947 August 7 - 1948 December 30 (Volume Volume 33)
  - Withholding tax notes, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - Time Book, 1949 January 6 - 1950 April 27 (Volume Volume 34)
  - Time Book, 1950 May 4 - 1951 September 27 (Volume Volume 35)
  - Salary Chart, 1950 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Tax Handbook, Withholding Table, 1951 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Time Book, 1951 October 2 - 1953 January 29 (Volume Volume 36)
  - Time Book, 1953 February 5 - 1953 March 27 (Volume Volume 37)
- Property Records, 1871-1940; Series VI
  - Lots 14 and 16, Block 22 (Magnolia and Champion), Deed & Transfer, 1930 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Mortgages to Ada C. Morse, regarding Block 22, 1922-1940 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Lots 1-24, Block 35, Deed & Transfer from June and Farrar Burn, 1929, 1935, 1936 (Box-folder 1/22)
  - Lots 11 and 12, Block 1 (Unity St), Deed & Transfer, 1937 (Box-folder 1/23)
  - Lots 11 and 12, Block 1, Central Whatcom, Abstract of Title, 1871-1937 (Box-folder 1/24)
  - Lots 8 and 9 in Alfs’ Grove Addition to Bellingham, Deeds and Transfers, 1909-1939 (Box-folder 1/25)
  - Transfer of LaConner Mail & Printing Plant, 1937-1940 (Box-folder 1/26)
  - Metsker’s Atlas of Whatcom County, May 1971 (Volume Volume 38)
- Publications, 1939-1948, undated; Series V
  - The Em Quad Company newsletter, 1939-1948 (Box-folder 1/27)
  - Latham Machine Company Catalog, undated (Box-folder 1/28)